long before the due date. That proves that this species of humanity is capable of achieving extraordinary progress if it really acts together and it really tries hard. But if I had to put it in a nutshell these days, I sort of feel that globalization has taken us by surprise, and we've been slow to respond to it. If you look at the downside of globalization, it really does seem to be sometimes overwhelming. All of the grand challenges that we face today, like climate change and human rights and demographics and terrorism and pandemics and narco-trafficking and human slavery and species loss, I could go on, we're not making an awful lot of progress against an awful lot of those challenges. So in a nutshell, that's the challenge that we all face today at this interesting point in history. That's clearly what we've got to do next. We've somehow got to get our act together and we've got to figure out how to globalize the solutions better so that we don't simply become a species which is the victim of the globalization of problems. Why are we so slow at achieving these advances? What's the reason for it? Well, there are, of course, a number of reasons, but perhaps the primary reason is because we're still organized as a species in the same way that we were organized 200 or 300 years ago. There's one superpower left on the planet and that is the seven billion people, the seven billion of us who cause all these problems, the same seven billion, by the way, who will resolve them all. But how are those seven billion organized? They're still organized in 200 or so nation-states, and the nations have governments that make rules and cause us to behave in certain ways. And that's a pretty efficient system, but the problem is that the way that those laws are made and the way those governments think is absolutely wrong for the solution of global problems, because it all looks inwards. The politicians that we elect and the politicians we don't elect, on the whole, have minds that microscope. They don't have minds that telescope. They look in. They pretend, they behave, as if they believed that every country was an island that existed quite happily, independently of all the others on its own little planet in its own little solar system. This is the problem: countries competing against each other, countries fighting against each other. This week, as any week you care to look at, you'll find people actually trying to kill each other from country to country, but even when that's not going on, there's competition between countries, each one trying to shaft the next. This is clearly not a good arrangement. We clearly need to change it. We clearly need to find ways of encouraging countries to start working together a little bit better. And why won't they do that? Why is it that our leaders still persist in looking inwards? Well, the first and most obvious reason is because that's what we ask them to do. That's what we tell them to do. When we elect governments or when we tolerate unelected governments, we're effectively telling them that what we want is for them to deliver us in our country a certain number of things. We want them to deliver prosperity, growth, competitiveness, transparency, justice and all of those things. So unless we start asking our governments to think outside a little bit, to consider the global problems that will finish us all if we don't start considering them, then we can hardly blame them if what they carry on doing is looking inwards, if they still have minds that microscope rather than minds that telescope. That's the first reason why things tend not to change. The second reason is that these governments, just like all the rest of us, are cultural psychopaths. I don't mean to be rude, but you know what a psychopath is. A psychopath is a person who, unfortunately for him or her, lacks the ability to really empathize with other human beings. When they look around, they don't see other human beings with deep, rich, three-dimensional personal lives and aims and ambitions. What they see is cardboard cutouts, and it's very sad and it's very lonely, and it's very rare, fortunately. But actually, aren't most of us not really so very good at empathy? Oh sure, we're very good at empathy when it's a question of dealing with people who kind of look like us and kind of walk and talk and eat and pray and wear like us, but when it comes to people who don't do that, who don't quite dress like us and don't quite pray like us and don't quite talk like us, do we not also have a tendency to see them ever so slightly as cardboard cutouts too? And this is a question we need to ask ourselves. I think constantly we have to monitor it. Are we and our politicians to a degree cultural psychopaths? The third reason is hardly worth mentioning because it's so silly, but there's a belief amongst governments that the domestic agenda and the international agenda are incompatible and always will be. This is just nonsense. In my day job, I'm a policy adviser. I've spent the last 15 years or so advising governments around the world, and in all of that time I have never once seen a single domestic policy issue that could not be more imaginatively, effectively and rapidly resolved than by treating it as an international problem, looking at the international context, comparing what others have done, bringing in others, working externally instead of working internally. And so you may say, well, given all of that, why then doesn't it work? Why can we not make our politicians change? Why can't we demand them? Well I, like a lot of us, spend a lot of time complaining about how hard it is to make people change, and I don't think we should fuss about it. I think we should just accept that we are an inherently conservative species. We don't like to change. It exists for very sensible evolutionary reasons. We probably wouldn't still be here today if we weren't so resistant to change. It's very simple: Many thousands of years ago, we discovered that if we carried on doing the same things, we wouldn't die, because the things that we've done before by definition didn't kill us, and therefore as long as we carry on doing them, we'll be okay, and it's very sensible not to do anything new, because it might kill you. But of course, there are exceptions to that. Otherwise, we'd never get anywhere. And one of the exceptions, the interesting exception, is when you can show to people that there might be some self-interest in them making that leap of faith and changing a little bit. So I've spent a lot of the last 10 or 15 years trying to find out what could be that self-interest that would encourage not just politicians but also businesses and general populations, all of us, to start to think a little more outwardly, to think in a bigger picture, not always to look inwards, sometimes to look outwards. And this is where I discovered something quite important. In 2005, I launched a study called the Nation Brands Index. What it is, it's a very large-scale study that polls a very large sample of the world's population, a sample that represents about 70 percent of the planet's population, and I started asking them a series of questions about how they perceive other countries. And the Nation Brands Index over the years has grown to be a very, very large database. It's about 200 billion data points tracking what ordinary people think about other countries and why. Why did I do this? Well, because the governments that I advise are very, very keen on knowing how they are regarded. They've known, partly because I've encouraged them to realize it, that countries depend enormously on their reputations in order to survive and prosper in the world. If a country has a great, positive image, like Germany has or Sweden or Switzerland, everything is easy and everything is cheap. You get more tourists. You get more investors. You sell your products more expensively. If, on the other hand, you have a country with a very weak or a very negative image, everything is difficult and everything is expensive. So governments care desperately about the image of their country, because it makes a direct difference to how much money they can make, and that's what they've promised their populations they're going to deliver. So a couple of years ago, I thought I would take some time out and speak to that gigantic database and ask it, why do some people prefer one country more than another? And the answer that the database gave me completely staggered me. It was 6.8. I haven't got time to explain in detail. Basically what it told me was — (Laughter) (Applause) — the kinds of countries we prefer are good countries. We don't admire countries primarily because they're rich, because they're powerful, because they're successful, because they're modern, because they're technologically advanced. We primarily admire countries that are good. What do we mean by good? We mean countries that seem to contribute something to the world in which we live, countries that actually make the world safer or better or richer or fairer. Those are the countries we like. This is a discovery of significant importance — you see where I'm going — because it squares the circle. I can now say, and often do, to any government, in order to do well, you need to do good. If you want to sell more products, if you want to get more investment, if you want to become more competitive, then you need to start behaving, because that's why people will respect you and do business with you, and therefore, the more you collaborate, the more competitive you become. This is quite an important discovery, and as soon as I discovered this, I felt another index coming on. I swear that as I get older, my ideas become simpler and more and more childish. This one is called the Good Country Index, and it does exactly what it says on the tin. It measures, or at least it tries to measure, exactly how much each country on Earth contributes not to its own population but to the rest of humanity. Bizarrely, nobody had ever thought of measuring this before. So my colleague Dr. Robert Govers and I have spent the best part of the last two years, with the help of a large number of very serious and clever people, cramming together all the reliable data in the world we could find about what countries give to the world. And you're waiting for me to tell you which one comes top. And I'm going to tell you, but first of all I want to tell you precisely what I mean when I say a good country. I do not mean morally good. When I say that Country X is the goodest country on Earth, and I mean goodest, I don't mean best. Best is something different. When you're talking about a good country, you can be good, gooder and goodest. It's not the same thing as good, better and best. This is a country which simply gives more to humanity than any other country. I don't talk about how they behave at home because that's measured elsewhere. And the winner is Ireland. (Applause) According to the data here, no country on Earth, per head of population, per dollar of GDP, contributes more to the world that we live in than Ireland. What does this mean? This means that as we go to sleep at night, all of us in the last 15 seconds before we drift off to sleep, our final thought should be, godammit, I'm glad that Ireland exists. (Laughter) And that — (Applause) — In the depths of a very severe economic recession, I think that there's a really important lesson there, that if you can remember your international obligations whilst you are trying to rebuild your own economy, that's really something. Finland ranks pretty much the same. The only reason why it's below Ireland is because its lowest score is lower than Ireland's lowest score. Now the other thing you'll notice about the top 10 there is, of course, they're all, apart from New Zealand, Western European nations. They're also all rich. This depressed me, because one of the things that I did not want to discover with this index is that it's purely the province of rich countries to help poor countries. This is not what it's all about. And indeed, if you look further down the list, I don't have the slide here, you will see something that made me very happy indeed, that Kenya is in the top 30, and that demonstrates one very, very important thing. This is not about money. This is about attitude. This is about culture. This is about a government and a people that care about the rest of the world and have the imagination and the courage to think outwards instead of only thinking selfishly. I'm going to whip through the other slides just so you can see some of the lower-lying countries. There's Germany at 13th, the U.S. comes 21st, Mexico comes 66th, and then we have some of the big developing countries, like Russia at 95th, China at 107th. Countries like China and Russia and India, which is down in the same part of the index, well, in some ways, it's not surprising. They've spent a great deal of time over the last decades building their own economy, building their own society and their own polity, but it is to be hoped that the second phase of their growth will be somewhat more outward-looking than the first phase has been so far. And then you can break down each country in terms of the actual datasets that build into it. I'll allow you to do that. From midnight tonight it's going to be on goodcountry.org, and you can look at the country. You can look right down to the level of the individual datasets. Now that's the Good Country Index. What's it there for? Well, it's there really because I want to try to introduce this word, or reintroduce this word, into the discourse. I've had enough hearing about competitive countries. I've had enough hearing about prosperous, wealthy, fast-growing countries. I've even had enough hearing about happy countries because in the end that's still selfish. That's still about us, and if we carry on thinking about us, we are in deep, deep trouble. I think we all know what it is that we want to hear about. We want to hear about good countries, and so I want to ask you all a favor. I'm not asking a lot. It's something that you might find easy to do and you might even find enjoyable and even helpful to do, and that's simply to start using the word "good" in this context. When you think about your own country, when you think about other people's countries, when you think about companies, when you talk about the world that we live in today, start using that word in the way that I've talked about this evening. Not good, the opposite of bad, because that's an argument that never finishes. Good, the opposite of selfish, good being a country that thinks about all of us. That's what I would like you to do, and I'd like you to use it as a stick with which to beat your politicians. When you elect them, when you reelect them, when you vote for them, when you listen to what they're offering you, use that word, "good," and ask yourself, "Is that what a good country would do?" And if the answer is no, be very suspicious. Ask yourself, is that the behavior of my country? Do I want to come from a country where the government, in my name, is doing things like that? Or do I, on the other hand, prefer the idea of walking around the world with my head held high thinking, "Yeah, I'm proud to come from a good country"? And everybody will welcome you. And everybody in the last 15 seconds before they drift off to sleep at night will say, "Gosh, I'm glad that person's country exists." Ultimately, that, I think, is what will make the change. That word, "good," and the number 6.8 and the discovery that's behind it have changed my life. I think they can change your life, and I think we can use it to change the way that our politicians and our companies behave, and in doing so, we can change the world. I've started thinking very differently about my own country since I've been thinking about these things. I used to think that I wanted to live in a rich country, and then I started thinking I wanted to live in a happy country, but I began to realize, it's not enough. I don't want to live in a rich country. I don't want to live in a fast-growing or competitive country. I want to live in a good country, and I so, so hope that you do too. Thank you. (Applause)
mucho antes del plazo establecido. Eso demuestra que esta especie de la humanidad puede lograr avances extraordinarios si realmente actúa en conjunto y se esfuerza mucho. Pero si tuviera que decirlo en pocas palabras, actualmente, siento que la globalización nos ha tomado por sorpresa, y hemos respondido con lentitud. Si miramos los efectos negativos de la globalización, a veces realmente parece ser abrumadora. Frente a los grandes desafíos que enfrentamos hoy, como el cambio climático y los derechos humanos la demografía, el terrorismo y las pandemias, el narcotráfico y la esclavitud humana, la pérdida de especies, y podría seguir, no estamos haciendo un gran avance ante gran cantidad de esos desafíos. Por eso, en pocas palabras, ese es el desafío que enfrentamos hoy en este punto interesante de la historia. Eso es claramente lo que tenemos que hacer a continuación. De algún modo tenemos que actuar juntos y descubrir cómo globalizar mejor las soluciones para no ser solo una especie víctima de la globalización de los problemas. ¿Por qué avanzamos tan lentamente? ¿Cuál es la razón? Bueno, hay, claro, varias razones, pero quizá la razón principal es que como especie aún estamos organizados de la misma manera que hace 200 o 300 años. Queda una superpotencia en el planeta y somos los 7000 millones de personas, los 7000 millones que causamos estos problemas, los mismos 7000 millones, por cierto, que los resolveremos. ¿Pero cómo nos organizamos los 7000 millones? Nos organizamos en 200 o más naciones, y las naciones tienen gobiernos que hacen leyes que nos hacen comportar de cierta manera. Y es un sistema bastante eficiente, pero el problema es que la redacción de esas leyes y la forma de pensar de los gobiernos es totalmente errónea para la solución de problemas globales, porque todo eso mira hacia adentro. Los políticos que elegimos y los que no elegimos, en conjunto, piensan en lo microscópico. No tienen mentes telescópicas. Miran hacia adentro. Fingen, se comportan, como si creyeran que cada país es una isla que existe muy feliz, independiente de todos los otros en su propio y pequeño planeta en su propio y pequeño sistema solar. Este es el problema: los países compiten unos contra otros, los países luchan unos contra otros. Esta semana, como cualquier semana que miren, encontrarán personas que tratan de matarse unos a otros de país a país y, si no pasa eso, hay una competencia entre países, cada uno tratando de maltratar al otro. Claramente no es una buena configuración. Claramente tenemos que cambiarla. Claramente tenemos que encontrar la forma de alentar a los países a empezar a trabajar juntos un poquito mejor. ¿Y por qué no lo harán? ¿Por qué nuestros líderes todavía siguen mirando hacia adentro? Bueno, la primera razón y la más obvia es porque nosotros se lo pedimos. Les decimos que hagan eso. Cuando elegimos gobiernos, o cuando toleramos gobiernos no electos, efectivamente les decimos que queremos que le den a nuestro país determinadas cosas. Queremos prosperidad, crecimiento, competitividad, transparencia, justicia y todo eso. Por eso, a menos que empecemos a pedirles que piensen hacia afuera un poquito más, que consideren los problemas globales que tendremos si no empezamos a pensar en ellos, entonces difícilmente podamos culparlos si siguen mirando hacia adentro, si todavía miran lo microscópico en vez de mirar lo telescópico. Esa es la primera razón por la que las cosas no cambian. La segunda razón es que estos gobiernos, como el resto de nosotros, son psicópatas culturales. Yo no quiero ser grosero, pero ya saben lo que es un psicópata. Un psicópata es una persona que desafortunadamente para él o ella, no puede lograr empatía con otros seres humanos. Cuando miran alrededor no ven a otros seres humanos con vidas profundas, ricas, tridimensionales, con objetivos y ambiciones. Ven en cambio recortes de cartón, es algo muy triste y solitario, y es muy poco frecuente, afortunadamente. Pero, en realidad, ¿no somos la mayoría no tan buenos en empatía? Claro, somos buenos en empatía para tratar con personas que se nos parecen que caminan, comen y rezan como nosotros, pero si se trata de personas que no lo hacen así, que no se visten como nosotros, que no rezan como nosotros, que no hablan como nosotros, ¿no tendemos también a verlos levemente como recortes de cartón? Es una pregunta que tenemos que hacernos. Pienso que tenemos que vigilar esto constantemente. ¿Somos nosotros y nuestros políticos en cierto punto psicópatas culturales? La tercera razón no es muy digna de mención por ser muy tonta, pero hay una creencia en los gobiernos de que la agenda local y la agenda internacional son incompatibles y siempre lo serán. Esto no tiene sentido. En mi trabajo diario soy asesor de política. He pasado los últimos 15 años asesorando a gobiernos de todo el mundo, y en todo ese tiempo nunca he visto un solo problema de política local que no pueda ser resuelto más imaginativamente con más eficiencia y rapidez que tratándolo como un problema internacional, mirando el contexto internacional, comparando con lo que han hecho otros, incluyendo a otros, trabajando en el ámbito externo en vez de hacerlo en el interno. Teniendo en cuenta todo eso podrán decir: ¿Por qué entonces no funciona? ¿Por qué no podemos hacer cambiar a nuestros políticos? ¿Por qué no se lo pedimos? Bueno, yo como muchos, paso mucho tiempo quejándome de lo difícil que es hacer que la gente cambie, y no creo que tengamos que preocuparnos por eso. Pienso que deberíamos aceptar que pertenecemos a una especie inherentemente conservadora. No nos gusta el cambio. Es así por razones evolutivas muy sensatas. Probablemente no estaríamos aquí hoy de no haber resistido tanto el cambio. Es muy simple: Hace miles de años, descubrimos que si continuábamos haciendo las mismas cosas no moriríamos, porque las cosas que hicimos antes por definición no nos mataron, y por lo tanto si seguíamos haciendo eso, estaríamos bien, y era muy sensato no hacer nada nuevo, porque podría matarnos. Pero claro, hay excepciones. De lo contrario, nunca llegaríamos a ninguna parte. Y una de las excepciones, la excepción interesante, es cuando podemos mostrarle a las personas que puede haber un poco de interés propio en dar ese salto de fe y cambiar un poco. Hemos pasado gran parte de los últimos 10 o 15 años tratando de descubrir cuál podría ser ese interés propio que pudiera alentar tanto a políticos como a empresas y a la población en general, a todos nosotros, a pensar un poco más hacia afuera, a pensar en el panorama general, no siempre mirar hacia adentro, y a veces mirar hacia afuera. Y fue entonces que descubrí algo bastante importante. En 2005 lancé un estudio llamado Índice de Marca País. Es un estudio a muy gran escala que encuesta a una muestra muy grande de la población mundial, una muestra que representa a un 70 % de la población del planeta, y le empecé a hacer una serie de preguntas sobre cómo perciben a otros países. Y el Índice de Marca País con los años se ha convertido en una enorme base de datos. Tiene unas 200 000 millones de entradas que siguen la opinión de la gente común sobre otros países y por qué. ¿Por qué hago esto? Bueno, porque a los gobiernos que aconsejo les interesa mucho saber cómo los ven. Saben, en parte porque yo los he alentado a darse cuenta, que los países dependen enormemente de su reputación para sobrevivir y prosperar en el mundo. Si un país tiene una gran imagen positiva, como Alemania, Suecia o Suiza, todo es fácil y todo es barato. Uno recibe más turistas, y tiene más inversores. Uno vende sus productos más caros. Por el contrario, si uno tiene un país con una imagen muy débil o muy negativa, todo es difícil y todo es caro. Entonces los gobiernos se preocupan desesperadamente por la imagen del país, porque marca una diferencia directa en el dinero que pueden ganar, y eso es lo que le han prometido a sus poblaciones que harán. Por eso hace un par de años decidí tomarme un tiempo y hablar con esa base de datos gigante y preguntarle ¿por qué algunas personas prefieren a un país más que a otro? Y la respuesta que me dio esa base de datos me dejó anonadado. Fue 6,8. No tengo tiempo para explicarlo en detalle. Básicamente me dijo... (Risas) (Aplausos) que preferimos a los países buenos. No admiramos a los países principalmente porque sean ricos porque sean poderosos, porque sean exitosos, porque sean modernos, porque sean avanzados en tecnología. Admiramos principalmente a los países buenos. ¿Qué queremos decir con 'buenos'? Queremos decir países que parecen contribuir en algo al mundo en que vivimos, países que en realidad hacen al mundo más seguro o mejor o más rico o más justo. Esos son los países que nos gustan. Este es un descubrimiento de importancia significativa —ven hacia dónde voy— porque cierra el círculo. Ahora puedo decir, lo hago a menudo, a cualquier gobierno, para que te vaya bien tienes que hacer el bien. Si quieres vender más productos, si quieres recibir más inversiones, si quieres ser más competitivo, tienes que comportarte, porque de ese modo las personas te respetarán y harán negocios contigo, y por lo tanto, cuanto más colabores más competitivo serás. Este es un descubrimiento bastante importante y ni bien lo descubrí sentí que venía un nuevo índice. Juro que cuanto más viejo me pongo, más simples son mis ideas, cada vez más infantiles. Este es el Índice de País Bueno, y hace lo que dice en la etiqueta. Mide, o intenta medir, exactamente cuánto contribuye cada país de la Tierra no a su propia población sino al resto de la humanidad. Curiosamente, nadie había pensado nunca en medir esto antes. Por eso mi colega, el Dr. Robert Govers y yo, pasamos gran parte de los últimos dos años, junto a gran cantidad de personas muy serias e inteligentes, consolidando todos los datos confiables del mundo que pudimos encontrar sobre lo que dan los países al mundo. Estarán esperando que les diga quiénes están en la cima. Y se los diré pero primero quiero contarles precisamente qué quiero decir cuando digo país bueno. No me refiero a moralmente bueno. Cuando digo que el País X es el país más bueno de la Tierra digo el más bueno, no el mejor. El mejor es algo distinto. Cuando uno habla de un país bueno, puede ser bueno, más bueno o el más bueno. No es lo mismo que bueno, mejor y el mejor. Este es simplemente un país que da más a la humanidad que cualquier otro país. No hablo de cómo se comportan localmente porque eso se mide en otros lados. Y el ganador es: Irlanda. (Aplausos) Según estos datos, ningún país de la Tierra, por habitante, por dólar de PBI, contribuye más al mundo en el que vivimos que Irlanda. ¿Qué significa esto? Significa que cuando vamos a dormir por la noche todos, en los últimos 15 segundos antes de conciliar el sueño, nuestro último pensamiento debería ser me alegro de que exista Irlanda. (Risas) Y eso... (Aplausos) en lo profundo de una recesión económica muy grave pienso que da una lección realmente muy importante el hecho de recordar las obligaciones internacionales mientras tratas de reconstruir tu economía, es algo importante. Finlandia está ubicada casi igual. La única razón por la que está debajo de Irlanda es porque su puntuación más baja está por debajo de la más baja de Irlanda. Lo otro que notarán en los 10 primeros es, claro, son todos, salvo Nueva Zelanda, países de Europa occidental. Todos son ricos. Esto me deprimió porque una de las cosas que no quería descubrir con este índice era la providencia de los países ricos que ayudan a los países pobres. No tiene que ver con esto. Y de hecho, si miramos más abajo en la lista, no tengo la diapositiva aquí, verán algo que, de hecho, me puso muy feliz: Kenia está entre los 30 primeros, y eso demuestra algo muy, muy importante. No se trata de dinero. Tiene que ver con la actitud. Tiene que ver con la cultura. Tiene que ver con un gobierno y unas personas que se ocupan del resto del mundo y tienen la imaginación y el coraje y piensan hacia afuera en vez de solo pensar en forma egoísta. Pasaré rápido las otras diapositivas para que puedan ver algunos países más abajo en la lista. Alemania está 13, EE.UU. 21, México 66, y luego tenemos algunos grandes países en desarrollo como Rusia 95, China 107. Que países como China, Rusia e India estén abajo en la misma parte del índice, bueno, en cierta forma no sorprende. Han pasado mucho tiempo en las últimas décadas construyendo su propia economía, construyendo su propia sociedad y su propia política, pero es de esperar que en la segunda fase de su crecimiento miren un poco más hacia afuera que en la primera fase. Y luego pueden analizar cada país en términos de los datos reales que los constituyen. Les permitiré que lo hagan. A partir de la medianoche estará en goodcountry.org, y pueden mirar su país. Pueden llegar hasta el nivel de los datos individuales. Este es el Índice de País Bueno. ¿Para qué está? Bueno, está porque quiero tratar de introducir esta palabra o reintroducir esta palabra al discurso. Ya he escuchado demasiado sobre países competitivos. Ya he escuchado demasiado sobre países prósperos, ricos, que crecen rápidamente. He escuchado demasiado sobre países felices porque al final eso sigue siendo egoísta. Eso sigue siendo sobre nosotros, y si seguimos pensando en nosotros, estamos en un problema muy profundo. Pienso que sabemos sobre qué queremos escuchar. Queremos escuchar sobre países buenos, por eso quiero pedirles un favor. No pido mucho. Es algo que puede resultar fácil de hacer y que incluso podrían encontrar agradable e incluso útil, y es empezar a usar la palabra "bueno" en este contexto. Cuando piensen en su propio país, cuando piensen en los países de otros, cuando piensen en las empresas, cuando hablen del mundo en el que vivimos hoy, empiecen a usar esa palabra en el modo en que les conté esta tarde. No bueno, lo opuesto a malo, porque esa es una discusión interminable. Bueno, lo opuesto a egoísta, bueno como país que piensa en todos nosotros. Eso es lo que me gustaría que hagan, y me gustaría que lo usen como una tabla para golpear a sus políticos. Cuando los eligen, cuando los reeligen, cuando los votan, cuando escuchan lo que les ofrecen, usen esa palabra, "bueno", y pregúntense: "¿Esto es lo que haría un buen país?" Y si la respuesta es no, sospechen. Pregúntense, ¿es el comportamiento de mi país? Quiero pertenecer a un país cuyo gobierno, en mi nombre, hace cosas como esas? O, por otro lado, prefiero la idea de caminar por el mundo con la cabeza en alto pensando: "Sí, siento orgullo de pertenecer a un país bueno". Y todos les darán la bienvenida. Y todos en los últimos 15 segundos antes de conciliar el sueño por la noche dirán: "Dios, estoy feliz de que el país de esta persona exista". En última instancia, eso, pienso, es lo que generará el cambio. La palabra "bueno", el número 6,8 y el descubrimiento subyacente cambiaron mi vida. Pienso que puede cambiar sus vidas, y pienso que podemos usarlo para cambiar el comportamiento de nuestros políticos y empresas y, al hacerlo, podemos cambiar el mundo. Empecé a pensar muy diferente sobre mi propio país al pensar en estas cosas. Solía pensar que quería vivir en un país rico, y luego que quería vivir en un país feliz, pero empecé a darme cuenta de que eso no es suficiente. No quiero vivir en un país rico. No quiero vivir en un país que crece rápido o que es competitivo. Quiero vivir en un país bueno, y espero que Uds. también. Gracias. (Aplausos)